Guide to the Hubert Hayes Papers, 1891-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hubert Hayes papers 1891-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hayes, Hubert, 1901-1964
21.0 linear feet Extent: 4,625 Items
Author, playwright, and founder and director of the Mountain Youth Jamboree. The Hubert Hayes Papers span the years 1891-1983 and document the life and career of Hubert Hayes and to some extent of his wife Leona Hayes. Includes professional and personal correspondence; drafts of plays, short stories and other writings by Hayes; plays by other authors; folders and scrapbooks of photographs, clippings, archives and programs for the Hubert Hayes Mountain Youth Jamboree, founded by Hayes and directed after his death by his widow, Leona T. Hayes; audio tapes of the Jamboree (original reels closed to use; use copies must be made); scripts, promotional materials, production notes, and clippings relating to the productions of Hayes' plays Tight Britches and Thunderland; photographs of friends and relatives; photograph of the Trinity College football team in 1922 or 1923; photographs of Thomas Wolfe taken in the summer of 1937; items concerning the Hubert Hayes Memorial Cabin at the Asheville-Biltmore Botanical Gardens (later moved to the Western Carolina University Mountain Heritage Center); a carving by Mary U. Chiltoskey of Cherokee, N.C., on a block of maple taken from Hayes' work bench; items concerning the National Folk Festival Association; notebook containing information about the life and career of Leona T. Hayes; and letters to Mrs. Hayes from Benjamin E. Powell, former Librarian of Duke University, and other items relating to the Friends of Duke University Library.
RL.00522
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Audiovisual originals are closed to use. Use copies must be made before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hubert Hayes Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Collection Overview
The papers span the years 1891-1983 and document the life and career of Hubert Hayes and to some extent of his wife, Leona Hayes. Includes professional and personal correspondence; drafts of plays, short stories and other writings by Hayes; plays by other authors; scrapbooks and folders of photographs, clippings, archives and programs for the Hubert Hayes Mountain Youth Jamboree, founded by Hayes and directed after his death by his widow, Leona T. Hayes; audio tapes of the Jamboree (original reels closed to use; use copies must be made); scripts, promotional materials, production notes, and clippings relating to the productions of Hayes' plays Tight Britches and Thunderland (the latter is about Daniel Boone); photographs of friends and relatives; photograph of the Trinity College football team in 1922 or 1923; photographs of Thomas Wolfe taken in the summer of 1937; items concerning the Hubert Hayes Memorial Cabin at the Asheville-Biltmore Botanical Gardens (later moved to the Western Carolina University Mountain Heritage Center); a carving by Mary U. Chiltoskey of Cherokee, N.C., on a block of maple taken from Hayes' work bench; items concerning the National Folk Festival Association; notebook containing information about the life and career of Leona T. Hayes; and letters to Mrs. Hayes from Benjamin E. Powell, former Librarian of Duke University, and other items relating to the Friends of Duke University Library.
Subject Headings
Hayes, Hubert, 1901-1964; Hayes, Leona T.; Wolfe, Thomas, 1900-1938; Powell, Benjamin Edward, 1905-; Hubert Hayes Mountain Youth Jamboree; National Folk Festival Association; Western Carolina University. Mountain Heritage Center; Friends of Duke University Library; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Sports; Folk festivals -- North Carolina; Authors, American -- North Carolina; Audio recordings
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1954-1970, (3 boxes)
  - 1934-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1970 (Box 2)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 3)
- Writings Series, (17 boxes) (Box 3)
  - Writings By Author Subseries (Box 3)
    - Thunderland (Box 3)
      - Clippings (Box 4)
      - Promotion and production papers (Box 6-7)
      - Research data (Box 13)
      - Scripts (Box 14-15)
      - Scripts and music (Box 16)
    - Tight Britches (Box 5)
      - Scripts (Box 5)
      - Devils Courthouse, antecedent of Tight Britches (Box 5)
      - Promotion and production papers (Box 12)
      - Clippings (Box 12)
    - Where Vanishes the Flame (Box 8)
      - Script and notes (Box 8)
      - Scripts (Box 9)
    - Short plays (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous writings, including What Billy Graham Did for Me (Box 11)
    - Huckleberry Mountain Workshop, camp folder (Box 11)
    - Foxfire (Box 17)
      - Scripts (Box 17)
      - Miscellany (Box 18)
    - Red Spider, scripts and royalty checks (Box 18)
  - Writings by Others Subseries (Box 18)
    - Play and music (Box 20)
    - Plays (Box 22)
- Miscellaneous Series, (2 boxes) (Box 22)
  - Biographical Data (Box 19)
  - Medical Data (Box 19)
  - Clippings (Box 21)
  - Miscellany (Box 21)
- Mountain Youth Jamboree Papers Series, (8 boxes) (Box 21)
  [Audiovisual originals are CLOSED to use. Use copies must be made before contents can be accessed.]
  - Papers (Box 23-30)
- Addition, 1954-1972, (6 boxes) (Box 23-30)
  - Papers, 1968 (Box 31)
  - Audio tapes (reels?), 1968 (Box 31)
  - Audio tapes of Hubert Hayes Mountain Youth Jamboree (Box 32)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 32)
    - 1954, 1962 (Box 33)
    - 1966 Apr. 20-23 (Box 34)
    - 1969 (Box 35)
    - 1962, 1965 Mar. 31- Apr. 3 (Box 36)
  - Partial index of ten reels, 1954, 1962 and 1965 (Box 36)
- Addition, 1958-1983, (17 boxes) (Box 36)
  - City auditorium papers, Asheville NC (Box 37-42, 47)
  - Tapes (reels?), 1967 (Box 43-44)
  - Papers (Box 45)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 45)
    - 1958-1983 (Box 46)
  - Short plays (including minstrel show material) and short stories (Box 48)
  - Lost Treasure of Peep Eye Cove (Box 49)
  - Printed material (Box 50)
  - Carving by Mary U. (Mrs. J.D.) Chiltoskey on a block from the work bench of H.H. Hayes (Box 51)
  - Volumes (Box 52)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 53)
- 1986 Addition, (1 box) (Box 53)
  - Scrapbooks, 1951-1953 (Box 54)
    Two scrapbooks of clippings, programs, flyers, and other ephemera relating to the production of Thunderland (1952), a play by Hubert Hayes about Daniel Boone, and one scrapbook with written narrative, postcards, and clippings covering a 1951 trip to Washington, DC by the Mountain Jamboree players, under Hayes' direction.